<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Memorial for the members to be chosen to represent this church, at the ensuing General Assembly, humbly offered, by an Elder of the Church of Scotland.</title>
            <author>Elder of the Church of Scotland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79738</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4231BA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC T201223</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45578254</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45578254</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172197</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79738)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172197)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2617:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Memorial for the members to be chosen to represent this church, at the ensuing General Assembly, humbly offered, by an Elder of the Church of Scotland.</title>
                  <author>Elder of the Church of Scotland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Publication information suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland. --  General Assembly.</term>
               <term>Ecclesiastical courts --  Scotland --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:172197:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>MEMORIAL FOR The Members to be Choſen TO Repreſent this CHURCH, at the enſuing General Aſſembly, HUMBLY OFFERED, BY <hi>An Elder of the Church of SCOTLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend and Honourable Fathers, and Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Crave Leave to be your Remembrancer with all dutiful Reſpect, as to ſome Things of great Weight in the preſent Juncture. 1ſt. It was the Glory of this Church, that for about Fifty Years together, after our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation from <hi>Popery,</hi> we continued free, both of Error and Schiſm. And afterwards, when <hi>Antichriſtian Prelacy,</hi> with other <hi>Romiſh</hi> Trumpery, was thruſt in upon us, and ſupported by the moſt cruel Perſecutions, and horrible Barbarities; yet ſome honeſt Teſtimony was born to our received Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline and Government. No Party amongſt us maintained Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Errors. Once indeed we had the ſharp Trial, that a Deluge of Errors and Hereſies broke in amongſt us, at the Advantage of a conquering Enemy, when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Sectaries got Footing here, and kept us under their Feet, for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:172197:2"/>Number of Years; nevertheleſs all that Time they could Proſelyte no Party amongſt us, to eſpouſe their Errors. A few, I confeſs, were charmed to ſome Liking of the Congregational Way. But as theſe were very inconſiderable, ſo neither did they continue. In the mean Time, the Church and Nation ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered to our Covenanted Doctrine and Diſcipline; and did alſo ſignalize them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for inviolable Loyalty amidſt many ſtrong Temptations from a victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Uſurper, at the Head of a powerful Army, fluſhed with unexpected Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes. But now while we enjoy Quietneſs and Liberty, it's Matter of heavy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grate, that the poiſonous Leaven of Error ſhould ferment and ſpread ſo ſtrongly. 2dly. It's humbly tendered to your ſerious Conſideration, That judicious and godly Perſons in forreign Places, think ſtrange, and lament, That this Church hath not taken the Affair of Profeſſor <hi>Simſon</hi> into their own Hands, and have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to appoint an Enquiry to be made in Name of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> into the Errors, he is alledged to have owned, and taught; Inſtead of which, they have obliged the Reverend Mr. <hi>Webſter</hi> to a laborious and difficult Purſuit, as if it had been a perſonal Affair of his, and did not equally, yea, and much more concern the whole Church. To ſet this Matter in ſome Evidence of Light, I tender the following Particulars to your ſerious Conſideration. 1ſt. This Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of proceeding was propoſed in full Aſſembly, when the Buſineſs of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor was tabled before them. The Reverend Mr. <hi>Webſter</hi> laid it at their Feet, as an important Concern of the whole Church, and declared his utter Averſion to intermedle in a perſonal Way; yet withal did ſignifie his hearty Willingneſs to give all the Aſſiſtance, that might be within his Reach, providing the Aſſembly would proceed in the Way deſired. 2dly. Neither was this the Sentiment of Mr. <hi>Webſter</hi> alone: Several Honourable and Grave Members of that Venerable Aſſembly were of the ſame Judgment. 3dly. With all due Reſpect to our very Reverend Aſſemblies, I repreſent, That perſonal Proſecutions in the Affair of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, are manifeſtly, and in the Nature of the Thing, obnoxious to ſuch Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies as are moſt hurtful to the Cauſe, and favourable on the Side of Error. I ſhall give but a few Hints, which I preſume ye will find very plain. This Method tends clearly towards the Prevention of any Purſuits in ſuch a Cauſe, conſidering how Matters are ſtated with poor ſinful Men. For in Regard of the Softneſs and Selfiſhneſs, with the Timidity of Nature in many; it is preſumable, That not one of an Hundred will adventure upon a Purſuit in this Caſe, when he knows before Hand, that the Church will not aſſiſt him as they refuſed to the Reverend Mr. <hi>Webſter.</hi> The Patrons of Error have ordinarly a ſtrong Party, who more openly, or ſecretly favour them, and they are aſſured of their utmoſt Aſſiſtance, ere they broach their own dangerous Opinions. The poiſonous Leaven hath uſually ſpread its Contagion very far, and gone deep ere it appear more openly; and they who may have Thoughts of a Purſuit, in ſuch Events,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:172197:2"/>are not readily ignorant of this, nor will fail to <hi>ſit down and count the Cost,</hi> ere they adventure on ſuch a difficult Project. Pleaſe take a little Glance. 1ſt. They muſt lay their Account to travel the Length of the Radical Judicatory, of which the Perſon accuſed is a Member; there they muſt attend, and in Caſe the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery favour the Party lybelled, the Purſuit is at the greateſt Diſadvantage, and the Purſuer may readily be diſcouraged, and ſuccumb, having no Aſſiſtance from the Church. But, to take the Matter by the very beſt Handle; what tho' he ſhould perſiſt, and finding himſelf leas'd, ſhould appeal to a higher Court; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide that he thereby ſtateth the Court appealed from, a Party againſt him, and is lyable to all the Exceptions they can make againſt his Management, which may perhaps defeat the Purſuit, becauſe of ſome Informalities, and bring himſelf into the Lurch. I ſay, beſides what's plainly ſuppoſable on this Head, though the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair ſhould be fairly brought to a higher Judicatory, and failing of Redreſs there, ſhould be carried to the higheſt in due Form; the Purſuer muſt ſtill follow it out, and attend all this while. And when the Proceſs is brought the Length of an Aſſembly, that great Court cannot find Leiſure to examine and cognoſce upon it: it muſt by them be referred to ſome Committee; and much depends upon the Choice of ſuch a Committee, which, if ſwaying, in a great Part towards the Side of the purſued, will embaraſs and intangle the Purſuer ſo much the more. Thus the Matter is toſſed from Committee to Committee: He is wiſe indeed, who can tell how long. Theſe are no fooliſh and remote Suppoſitions; whoever act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth wiſely, muſt lay his Account with them. 2dly. In regard ſuch Purſuits are reckoned very provocking, the Purſuer cannot readily eſcape all poſſible Recri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations by the purſued, and theſe who take his Part. He muſt lay his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, to have his Conduct canvaſſed and ſifted to the Outmoſt, and every Shadow graſped at, with the greateſt Eagerneſs, for bringing him under Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit. And if any thing can be found in his Management, that's juſtly exeptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable (which may readily befal) he muſt make his Reckoning, that ſuch Things will be aggravated to the higheſt Pinacle. And who knows what Lies and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies may be invented, and toſſed upon that Occaſion, and all to blacken the Purſuit, while in the mean Time, the Favourers of the purſued are buſied in venting their Legends, concerning his Piety, Learning and eminent Vertues. Theſe, with other ſuch Difficuties, will readily fall under the View of any, who deliberatly conſiders ſuch a Purſuit; which being maturely pondered, together with the great Fatigue and Expences he muſt needs undergo (and deſerve Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration in their own Place) will go far to deter one, or other, from intenting ſuch Proceſſes, in Matters which are no perſonal Concerns, but do equally, and yet more affect the whole Church, than any particular Member. Thus the poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous Leaven ſpreads, while no Man is like to make it his Buſineſs to ſtop the Diffuſion. And if the Church will not intereſt her ſelf, without ſome Purſuer, or
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172197:3"/>refuſeth to take the Load off from his Shoulders, who may adventure to ſtate a Proceſs. Behold, here a more effectual Toleration is granted to Error, than any that a State can inact, eſpecially if theſe deluding Interprizes be managed with Art, as they fail not to be. Error is a chief Project of lying, and murthering Spirits, for deſtroying the Churches of CHRIST; and they will take Care to chooſe the fitteſt Tools. I confeſs, That the Reſearches of Error ly open to Difficulties, in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Method they be Managed; eſpecially after theſe Tares are multiplied, and have taken ſtrong and deep Roots, through Neglect of the Watchmen: And the Cure of Eating Cankers is ſtill uneaſie. But ſo much the leſs Cauſe is there for rolling o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſuch a Buſineſs upon the Shoulders of any one Perſon. The harder the Work be, the more skilful Hands, and the greater Number are neceſſarly required; And the forementioned, or the like Difficulties are more eaſily prevented or redreſſed, under the Churches Management, than when ſuch Purſuits ly open to the Miſtakes of weaker Hands: So much for the Third Particular, <hi>viz.</hi> The Inconveniencies of Perſonal Proſecutions in this Affair. I ſhall <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Adventure a little higher, and make ſome Enquiry into the Divine Inſtitution about theſe Matters. I acknowledge, an Undertaking of ſo much Weight may readily ſuffer in ſo weak an Hand: Yet my poor Eſſay may give Occaſion to others for ſetting that Buſineſs in ſome full Evidence of Light. Were there any Divine Appointment or Perſonal Proſecutions in the preſent Matter. I ſhould ſoon yield the Cauſe, and plead no longer on the Score of Inconveniencies: But to me the Scriptures of Truth ſeem to look a quite contrary Way. 1ſt. The Body of Sound Interpreters do (ſo far as I have hitherto underſtood) carry the Lord's Commands, both with reſpect to Error, and other Diſorders. <hi>First,</hi> to the Church. <hi>A Man that is an</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>Heretick after the firſt or ſecond Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion reject,</hi> or caſt out. Theſe aſſuredly are Church Acts, and ſo underſtood by the Cloud of Faithful Interpeters. <hi>They</hi> ought to take Care of the LORD's Vineyard, and to <hi>take the little</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Song</hi> 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>Foxes, which ſpoil the tender Vines,</hi> What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Deficiencies may be in the Point of Delating, And touching Scandals in the Converſation of Profeſſing People, the Charge is given primarly to the Church, as our Eminent Divines have ſtill underſtood it. <hi>If any Man</hi> (ſaith th Apoſtle) <hi>obey not our Word by this Epiſtle</hi>
               <note place="bottom">¶ 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>Note that Man, &amp;c.</hi> Let the Church eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially put a Mark upon him. And what if none ſhould Complain? (ſuch may be the Degeneracy in particular Churches) muſt Scandals be Tolerated on that Pretext? Our Aſſemblies have intereſted themſelves in Points of Diſorder as to Church Communion, and have made theſe the Church's Buſineſs, and Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them in their own Name with Vigour enough. And muſt the Poyſonous Gangrene of Error be no Concern of the Church, and be ſuffered to ſpread, unleſs ſome Perſon (and under the heavieſt Diſcouragements) undertake the Proſecution. We our ſelves acknowledge, that a <hi>Fama Clamoſa</hi> my ſufficiently
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172197:3"/>found the Churches Purſuit in the Matter of Scandal: And is Error of no leſs moment? Sure it is more infectious. And (allow me to ſay it) there was more than a <hi>Fama Clamoſa</hi> in Mr. <hi>Simſon</hi>'s Caſe; for two Presbyteries Delated him to the Aſſembly, and inſtructed their Commiſſioners to move that the Church ſhould enquire into the Matter, and yet this may not be made the Churches Buſineſs! What can Impartial Beholders think! 2dly, The Deſignation of <hi>Watchmen</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.17. <hi>and</hi> 33.7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13, 17.</note> which the Spirit of GOD giveth to the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeers of the Church, beareth clearly the Obligation that lyeth upon them to make the Affair of Error their Buſineſs. It were a ſorry Inſpection of <hi>Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> ſhould they ſuffer a whole City to be Murthered, unleſs a Potent Poyſoner were Proſecuted before them by ſome particular Citizen? I need not enlarge a Remark ſo very obvious. 3dly, I Appeal to the firſt Chriſtian and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Aſſembly at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 15.1.</note> Here we have a leading Inſtance, and a clear Rule laid before us by an Aſſembly under the Conduct of Men Divinely Inſpir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and who might truly ſay, <hi>It ſeemed good unto the</hi>
               <note place="bottom">¶ <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5.28.</note> 
               <hi>Holy Ghoſt, and to us.</hi> An Error had ſprung up in the Primitive Virgin Church; Namely <hi>Certain Men which came from</hi> Judea <hi>had taught the Brethren: Except ye be</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>Circumciſed after the Manner of</hi> Moſes <hi>ye cannot be ſaved.</hi> What was the Management of the Apoſtles and Elders in this Caſe? Did they Siſt, until ſome one or other had the Courage to commence a Proceſs? Nay, the Church made the Affair it's own Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, and met about the Matter in a Judicative Capacity, as may be ſeen at more length in the Hiſtory. Suffer me a little to run the Parallel; <hi>Certain Men have ariſen amongſt us, who teach ſtrange, but no leſs, yea, and more Dangerous Doctrines: For Inſtance, they call in queſtion</hi> Adam's <hi>Federal Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Aſſert a ſure Connection between Moral Seriouſneſs and Saving Grace. They Aver, That the Number of the Saved is equal to, Yea, and greater than that of the Damned; And that all Infants Chriſtian and Heathen, dying in their Non-Age are Saved, heing Born in an Eſtate of Favour, from which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can caſt them out; But a Rejection of the offered Salvation; And that this Salvation is explicitely or implicitely offered unto all, both within, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Church, with a great deal more Rotten and Poyſonous</hi> Pelagian <hi>Stuff, all tending to exalt corrupt Nature.</hi> This is obſerved, Judicatories find Fault with it, ſome of them Attempt to lay it before the whole Repreſentative Church, yet they are born down and Diſcouraged. A great Party Conſpires to cruſh the very firſt Motions, tho' but humbly craving an Inquiry. Nevertheleſs it comes before our Aſſemblies at length; And their Conduct is ſuch, as I love not to Repeat. They will not make it their Buſineſs, nor do they attempt to Meet <hi>ex profeſſo</hi> upon that Head. Nay the Reverend Mr. <hi>Webſter</hi> who had but an equal Intereſt with others, tho' Honoured to ſtir more in that Matter: Mr. <hi>Webſter,</hi> I ſay, muſt be obliged to an uneaſie Purſuit, and the Aſſembly refuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172197:4"/>to grant his humble-Petition, earneſtly craving the Appointment of ſome little Aſſiſtance, tho' upon Solemn Promiſe to intereſt none in the Cauſe but himſelf. Now after all, dare we hold up our Faces, and think, or ſay, that, we have ſincerely followed the Scriptural Pattern in Profeſſor <hi>Simſon</hi>'s Affair. So much for this Head. I Repreſent 5ly. That the Churches of CHRIT from their firſt and Pureſt Times have endeavoured to follow the Apoſtolical Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern, and are not accuſtomed to make the Buſineſs of Error a Perſonal Buſineſs. Here I might give large and Circumſtanced Accounts from the firſt Records of Church Hiſtory to following Ages, and to Times, within the Compaſs of our own Memory. But, ſuch a Labour would carry me too far, and is not neceſſary, while I Write to Perſons much better Verſed in theſe Matters. Only allow me to give a ſlender Touch. This was not the Method of the firſt four Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Councils, ſo far as I could find, in the Matter of Error. Neither did the Renowned Synod which met at <hi>Dordreght,</hi> near the beginning of the laſt Age, oblige any to a Perſonal Proſecution of the <hi>Arminians,</hi> nor any Leader of them. That Church made it their own Buſineſs. And in our Times <hi>Roel</hi>'s and <hi>Leen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hof</hi>'s Errors were Condemned in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and Intrants into the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry obliged by the Claſſes there to Renounce them. There was no Perſonal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution in that Matter. And I remember that ſeveral Years ago, when I was occaſionally at <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> the <hi>Claſſis</hi> (or Presbytery) there, took Notice of ſome Erroneous Poſitions peeping out among the <hi>French</hi> Refugees, and obliged the Suſpected Perſons to Renounce them; As of Old, the <hi>Claſſis</hi> at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> had obliged <hi>Jacobus Arminius</hi> while he was one of the Miniſters of that City, to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Errors he had begun to vent. In all theſe Tranſactions no Load was laid upon any Perſon to ſtate and follow out a Proceſs, Yea, even our Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Brethren in <hi>New England</hi> (who are not the greateſt Friends to the Juſt Power of Church Judicatories) Yet in the Affair of Error, did meet in a General Synod, Condemned ſome dangerous Errors ſprung up amongſt them, and ordered a vigorous Proſecution by the ſeveral Churches of every one who preſumed to vent the Condemned Errors. I know it will be Objected, That our Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies have proceeded in this Matter, according to their own Acts, which were made upon mature Deliberation; and as it is preſumable, they knew beſt the Circumſtanced ſtate of this Church, to which they adjuſted them, ſo it may be juſtly accounted intollerable Preſumption in any Member of this Church at one daſh, to condemn the whole Church. I Anſwer, that I owe, and do ſincerely pay dutiful Reſpect to this Church and her Aſſemblies, tho' I Lament much want of the Zeal and Integrity which ſignalized us in former and purer Times. I am alſo well ſatisfied with the Act, which obligeth to Commence Proceſſes againſt Miniſters at the Radical Judicatories of which they are Members, and that the ſteps ſhould be taken, and Methods uſed, to which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172197:4"/>our Form of Proceſs directs. All this I Acknowledge, is wiſely Ordered and well Inacted by the very Reverend and Honourable Compilers, and ought to hold in ordinary Caſes, but as the choiceſt Rules of humane Framing, admit of ſome Exception; ſo there are Specialities in the Affair of Error, which render other Methods neceſſary. Scandals of Practice, are held in general Deteſtation, no Perſon pleads for them, and they are not ſo Infectious, but that the uſual Steps may be taken in the Proceſs, and competent time for that Effect may be beſtowed without Hurt. Purſuers may be alſo neceſſary in theſe Events, and yet the Church may proceed without them upon a <hi>fama clamoſa.</hi> Nevertheleſs, there are ſpecialities in the Matter of Error, which require that the Church ſhould make it her own Buſineſs. Errors are not ordinarly broached, until the Favourers of them be ſo Strengthened, that ſcarce any Accuſer ſhall dare to appear againſt them, eſpecially when at the forementioned or the like Diſadvantages; and thus the Poiſon deſtroys without Controul, unleſs the Church Interpoſe. Beſides, that a perſonal Proſecution in ſuch Caſes is ſo difficult, invidious, and lyable to ſuch manifold Checks, that few will be found, both able and willing for ſuch an Enterpriſe: And Perſons of Eminency, may readily be doubtful, whether the LORD call them to ſet their Faces againſt Streams ſo very ſtrong, or may be tempted to deſiſt from ſuch Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits in Caſe they enter upon them, becauſe of the Difficulties and Diſcouragements that attend theſe Proceſſes. Moreover, Errors in a Church are like a ſpreading Gangrene or a Houſe ſet on Fire. No delay may take place in ſuch Events, but all Hands ought to be at Work immediately, in the firſt place, to put a ſtop to the Progreſs, and afterwards to uſe the ſpeedieſt, and moſt effectul Methods for removing the Cauſes. This hard and important Work, the Churches of CHRIST have from the Beginning uſually accounted their own Buſineſs. 6ly. It may be conſidered, that ſome Errors vented by a late Probationer, and Publiſhed in a Print by him, and which were much of a bind with theſe alledged againſt Mr. <hi>Simſon:</hi> Theſe Errors, I ſay, were brought to a quicker Iſſue. The Reverend Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> Cognoſced upon them, and took that Probationer's Licenſe from him; That Buſineſs was managed without any Perſonal Purſuit. 7ly. It is earneſtly deſired by many Judicious and Godly in the Land, that beſides others, two Reſolutions and Deeds of the Reverend Committee in Mr. <hi>Simſon</hi>'s Affair, may be ſpecially conſidered, which ſeem to put a ſad and effectual Check upon any Proceſs in the Point of Error. 1st. The Erronious Poſitions charged on Mr. <hi>Simſon,</hi> were ſo Senſed by that Committee, and allowed to be Relevant only in theſe Senſes, That neither could the Probation by Witneſſes be Poſſible in theſe Events, for Witneſſes cannot prove a Senſe: And Moreover, ſeveral of theſe Senſes are ſo Conſtrained, That almoſt any Hetrodox Poſition, may be dragged into Orthodoxy by ſuch Strainings. 2dly. They reſolved, That no Probation by Witneſſes ſhould be admitted, unleſs the Witneſſes could Depone upon the <hi>Ipſiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172197:5"/>vert<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> without Addition, Dimin<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion or the leaſt Alteration. Now by ſuch dealing, tho' the groſſeſt Hereſies were Preached in the Hearing of Thouſands, it were a vain Attempt to intent a Proceſs againſt the Preacher; Seing it's fairly Preſumable, That Two concurring Witneſſes would not be eaſily found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them all that could Depone upon the very Words, without the Alteration of any one Particle. It's earneſtly deſired, that the Venerable Aſſembly would Remove theſe Obſtructions.</p>
            <p>After all, for as much as the Tares of Error are Sown, and Springing up in this Church, where the Increaſe muſt needs be Great, while the neceſſary Purſuits are at the Diſadvantages which render them almoſt utterly Impracticable. It is the humble and earneſt Deſire of many Judicious and Godly Perſons, both in this and other Churches, that not only the Affair of Profeſſor <hi>Simſon</hi> may be brought to a juſt Iſſue, but that alſo, the venerable enſuing Aſſembly would conſider and make ſuch Acts, as they in their Wiſdom, and under the Divine Conduct, may find Neceſſary and Proper, for Purging out that Poiſonous Leaven which hath Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented many amongſt us, and is ſtill ſpreading. I ſhall be very far from Preſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that Great and Venerable Court. I only Repreſent this plain Overture, with all dutiful Submiſſion, Namely, That they would Condemn by a Solemn Act, the ſpreading Errors, which are like to prevail amongſt us, and may be eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpecified upon no great Inquiry, and that they would appoint the Judicatories of this National Church, to take a cloſs and narrow Inſpection of the Miniſters and Members thereof, who may be Tainted with the ſame, after they have ſtrictly Prohibited the venting of ſuch Errors; And that they would nor ſuffer theſe Matters any longer, to depend upon Perſonal Proſecutions, which it is not to be thought, that any will Adventure upon, after the Diſcouragements which the preſent depending Purſuit hath Laboured under, and that they would oblige all Intrants into the Miniſtry to renounce theſe Errors.</p>
            <p>I ſhall Conclude with this one Remark; That the Aſſembly in the 15 of the <hi>Acts,</hi> the ſole Pattern in the Word of GOD we have for our General Aſſemblies, did not buſie themſelves with any thing but the ſuppreſſing of Error, for they Reckoned <hi>that</hi> an Affair of the higheſt Importance. And ſeing <hi>cuilibet licet ſupplicare,</hi> I do moſt humbly beg the Venerable Aſſembly, as they Tender the Purity of our Doctrine, and the Peace of this Church, to conſider the Affair Judicially, and by themſelves, without referring it to a Committee, and giving Implicite Faith to their Report; And tho' the bulk of the Committee's Procedure may frighten ſome Members, from granting this my humble deſire, yet the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viewing the Diſſents made by ſeveral Reverend and Worthy Members of the Committee formerly appointed, will not be a Work of ſo long a Time, as the Aſſembly in ſome Diets cannot conſider.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:172197:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
